A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources, 2013-2017 (bulk 2014-2017)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources, 2013-2017 (bulk 2014-2017)
The Library of Virginia
52207
4.9 cubic feet (14 Boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources on 22 January 2018.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governor's top management team. The Office of Secretary of Commerce and Resources was created on April 8, 1972. The Secretary of Commerce and Resources was responsible for assisting the Governor in implementing policies for the conservation and use of natural resources, for promoting economic development, providing managerial guidance and direction to Commerce and Resources agencies, and developing and promoting Commerce and Resources programs and budgets. In 1984 the Secretariat was split into two separate offices, the Secretary of Economic Development and the Secretary of Natural Resources. The Secretary of Natural Resources was responsible for the direction of, or had jurisdiction over, the following state agencies and boards: Department of Conservation and Recreation, Department of Environmental Quality, Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, Department of Historic Resources, Marine Resources Commission, Museum of Natural History, and the Virginia Council on Indians. The Secretary of Natural Resources also served as the chairman of the Virginia Land Conservation Foundation, and was a Board Member of the Chesapeake Bay Commission. Additionally, the Secretary of Natural Resources was responsible for many smaller boards and commissions related to water control, pollution, rivers, waste management, and other environmental and recreational issues.
Molly Ward, a native of Hampton, Virginia, served as Secretary of Natural Resources during the McAuliffe administration. She is a graduate of the University of Virginia and William and Mary Law School, and prior to her appointment, served as Hampton Treasurer, 2002-2008, and Hampton Mayor, 2008-2013. While mayor, Ward served on the Hampton Roads Planning District Commission and was appointed to the Virginia Outdoor Foundation by Governor Kaine.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Natural Resources records, 2013-2017, consist of 14 archival boxes and are divided into 4 series. Series have been designated for Correspondence (I), Scheduling (II), Subject files (III) and McDonnell Administration files (IV). These records document the work of Secretary of Natural Resources Molly Ward during the McAuliffe administration and were created or collected, 2013-2017, though some documents in this collection pre-date this time period.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence, 2013-2017
Series II. Scheduling, 2015-2017
Series III. Subject files, 2014-2017
Series IV. McDonnell Administration files, 2010-2013.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 2013-2017 (bulk 2014-2017)., Extent: 4 boxes (1.4 cu. ft.). (Box 1-4)
  Correspondence, 2013-2017, is housed in 4 archival box and is arranged chronologically. This series consists primarily of incoming correspondence and related attachments from local, state and federal government officials, state and federal legislators, officials from other states, business owners, and associations, as well as constituent correspondence that was sent either directly to the Secretary of Natural Resources or sent to the Governor and referred to the Secretary. Correspondence was accordingly forwarded to specific agencies for response based on topic. Also includes correspondence between the Secretary and agencies, as well as a few copies of outgoing correspondence and mass mailings, of which only a sample was retained. Attachments may include agreements, articles, budgets, legislation, memorandums of understanding, presentations, and reports. Topics include the Atlantic Pipeline, climate change, Chesapeake Bay, Clean Water Act, conservation and preservation funding, James River Water Authority, and wildlife conservation, among others. Mass mailing topics include the Atlantic Coast Pipeline, Clean Air Act, Clean Power Plan, and the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative.
  - Correspondence, 2013 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2014 May. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2014 June. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2014 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 2015 May. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 2015 June. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 2015 July. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2015 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Feb. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Mar. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2016 May. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2016 June. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2016 July. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Nov. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2016 Dec. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Student letters regarding the James River, 2016. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (no month specified), 2016. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2017 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2017 Feb. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2017 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2017 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2017 May. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 2017 June. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2017 July. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 2017 Sept. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 2017 Dec. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (no month specified), 2017. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - Atlantic Coast Pipeline, 2015 Mar-June. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - Atlantic Coast Pipeline, 2015 July-Oct. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Atlantic Coast Pipeline, 2016. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Clean Power Plan, 2016. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Clean Power Plan, 2016. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Clean Power Plan, 2016. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Curtis Timberlake, 2016. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Mass mailing (Atlantic Coast Pipeline), undated. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Mass mailing (Clean Air), undated. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Mass mailing (Clean Energy / Clean Power Plan (Sierra Club), 2016. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Mass mailing (Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative), 2015. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series II. Scheduling Office files, 2015-2017., Extent: 11 folders. (Box 5)
  Scheduling Office files, 2015-2017, are housed in 1 archival box (11 folders) and are arranged chronologically. This majority of this series consists of invitations, but also includes calendars, correspondence and event briefings with logistics and background information for events. Invitations often include notations as to whether accepted or declined. No files for transferred for 2014.
  - Scheduling - General, 2015-2016. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scheduling, 2015 May. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scheduling, 2015 June. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scheduling, 2015 July. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Scheduling, 2015 Aug. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scheduling, 2015 Sept. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scheduling, 2015 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Scheduling, 2015 Nov. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Scheduling, 2015 Dec. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Scheduling, 2016. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Scheduling, 2017. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series III. Subject files, 2014-2017., Extent: 5 boxes (1.75 cu. ft.) (Box 5-9)
  Subject files, 2014-2017, are housed in 5 archival boxes and are arranged alphabetically. Subject files include agreements, correspondence, financial statements, meeting records, presentations, project documentation, and reports. Topics include the Atlantic Pipeline, climate change, Chesapeake Bay, clean water, clean power, conservation and preservation funding, land conservation, monuments, Nottoway Indian Tribe, oysters, Potomac River, regulations, sustainibility, uranium mining, and wildlife conservation, among others.
  - Blue Ridge Land Conservancy, 2015-2017. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Brief - Repower South Project, 2016. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Capital Outlay Projects - Annual report, 2016. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Chesapeake Bay Commission, 2015-2017. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Chesapeake Bay Partnership, 2014. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Chesapeake Bay Restoration Fund - Advisory Committee, 2015-2016. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Chesapeake Conservancy, 2014. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Clean Power Plan, 2016. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Climate Change and Resiliency Update Commission meeting, 2015 Aug 31. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia Campaign - Certificates, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Decision brief - Dept. of Conservation and Recreation (Dutton residence), 2016. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Dishner v. Gate City, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Dishner v. Gate City, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Dishner v. Gate City, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Enrolled bills, 2017. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Executive Order 35 (2-14) - Continuation of the Virginia Coastal Zone Management Program, 2014. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Executive Order 52 (2016) - Workgroup / Development of Long-term Offsetting Methods with the Virginia Nutrient Credit Exchange Program, 2016. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Executive Order 57 (2016) - Workgroup / Development of Carbon Reduction Strategies for Electric Power Generation Facilities, 2016-2017. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Executive Order 57 (2016) - Workgroup / Development of Carbon Reduction Strategies for Electric Power Generation Facilities - Presentations, 2016. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Executive Order 57 (2016) - Workgroup / Development of Carbon Reduction Strategies for Electric Power Generation Facilities - Presentations, 2017. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Executive Order 57 (2016) - Workgroup / Development of Carbon Reduction Strategies for Electric Power Generation Facilities - Presentations, 2016-2017. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Financial reports, 2015-2016. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Game and Inland Fisheries, Dept. of - Headquarter Facility Condition Assessment, 2014 Aug. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Enterprise Strategic Priorities - Executive agreements, 2014. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Interstate Commission on the Potomac River Basin, 2015-2017. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Josephine City (Clarke County) (1 of 3), 2016. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Josephine City (Clarke County) (2 of 3), 2016. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Josephine City (Clarke County) (3 of 3), 2016. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Liberty University - Non-Compliant High Hazard Dam, 2015. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda of Agreement, 2014; undated. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Monuments Workgroup, 2016. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - National Park Service Centennial in Virginia, 2014. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Nottoway / Cheroenhaka Indian Tribe, 2013-2015. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Oysters, 2014. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Pipelines, 2016-2017. (Box 8, Folder 7a)
  - Possum Point coal ash ponds, 2015. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Potomac River Fisheries Commission, 2015. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Potomac River Fisheries Commission, 2016-2017. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - River Access and Virginia Treasures - Meeting, 2016 Apr 4. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Rivers of the Chesapeake - Collaborative Funding Proposal, 2014-2016. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Sustainability Tour, 2015-2016. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Trump Winery, 2014. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Agribusiness Council, 2016. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Institute of Marine Science, 2015-2017. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation, 2015. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Viginia Marine Resources Commission, 2016. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Marine Resources Commission - License registration, 2014. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Uranium, Inc., 2015. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Volkswagon, 2016. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated. (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Series IV. McDonnell Administration files, 2010-2013., Extent: 4 boxes (1.4 cu. ft.). (Box 10-13)
  McDonnell Administration files, 2010-2013, are housed in 4 archival boxes and are arranged alphabetically. These files were retained from the previous administration. This series includes correspondence, and project and topical files that contain briefs, correspondence, conference materials, executive orders, financial materials, legislation, meeting records, notes, presentations and reports. Topics include Chesapeake Bay, conservation, energy, Fort Monroe, Potomac River, surplus real property, uranium mining, and the Virginia Council on Indians.
  - Correspondence, 2010. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2011. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2012. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2013 Jan-May. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2013 June-July. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2013 Aug-Dec. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - America the Beautiful Quarters Program, 2012. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Appointments, 2013. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Biography - David K. Paylor, undated. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Cabinet continuity, 2010. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Captain John Smith Chesapeake National Historic Trail, 2013 Dec. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Caridal Horizon, 2011. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Chesapeake Bay - Total Max Daily Load, 2010-2012. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of, 2013. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Dominion Energy - Virginia City Hybrid Energy Center, 2010. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Dominion Energy - Warren County Power Station, 2011. (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Earth Day, 2010. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Energy - Virginia: Energy Capital of the East Coast, undated. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Financial Statements, 2010. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Financial Statements, 2011. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Financial Statements, 2012. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Financial Statements, 2013. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Fort Christiana Historical Site, 2013. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Fort Monroe Authority - Correspondence, 2012-2013. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Fort Monroe Authority - Meeting, 2010 Aug 23. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Fort Monroe Authority - Meeting, 2011 Jan 6. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Fort Monroe Authority - Reuse Plan, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Fulcher, Valerie, 2013. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Game and Inland Fisheries, Dept. of, 2013. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Governor Decision Requests, 2013 Oct-Dec. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Guns in State Parks, 2010. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Hiring, 2010-2011. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Hopewell Regional Wastewater Treatment Facility, 2011. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Houchens, Cynthia, 2013. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Indian Tax Tribute, undated. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Kayak Run - New River, 2011. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Law Enforcement Activities Within Agencies Under the Secretary of Natural Resources, 2013. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Library of Virginia, 2012-2013. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Lyme disease, 2010. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Master Natural Resources Projects List, undated. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District - Board of Directors meeting, 2013 Apr 23. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Oil and gas rights, 2011. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Oil and gas rights, 2012-2013. (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Outer Continental Shelf, 2012-2013. (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Potomac River Fisheries Commission - Minutes, 2010 Dec 3. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Rose Dale Vision Report, 2013 Oct. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Secure Commonwealth Panel - Recurring Coastal Flooding Subpanel, 2013 Sept 25. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Shelburne Glebe (Loudoun Co.), 2011. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Smith Mountain Lake Shoreline Management Plan, 2003. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Staff meeting - Agenda, 2013 July 2. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Surplus Real Property, 2010. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Surplus Real Property, 2011. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Surplus Real Property, 2012. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Surplus Real Property, 2013. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Uranium Mining in Virginia, 2012. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Council on Indians, 2010-2011. (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Council on Indians, 2012. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Council on Indians, 2013. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Council on Indians - Recognition of Virginia Indian Tribes (Report), 2014 Jan. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation - Report, 2013 Sept. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Information Technologies Agency - Costs, 2012. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Performs, 2011. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Uranium, Inc., 2010. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Winegard letter, 2010. (Box 14, Folder 7)